Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is דף כז Daf
Chaf-Zayin 27, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 27, we pick up on כו עמוד ב
Chaf-Vav Amud-Bet at the end of the first of the wide lines,
אמר רב יהודה אימתי, Amar Rav Yehuda Eimatai, and we are working
off of the משנה Mishna that is listing people that are פסול
לעד pasul le-eid because of עבירות. aveirot. Specifically the משנה Mishna focuses
on types of things that are sins that they are doing
for
the sake of financial gain. So the משנה Mishna lists משחק בקוביא
misachek be-kubiya gamblers,
מלווה בריבית malveh be-ribbit somebody who lends money with ריבית ribbit which
is a clear איסור דאורייתא, issur de-oraita, מפריחי יונים mafrichai yonim which
is another type of gambler, סוחרי שביעית sochrai shevi'it and people that
do transactions on שמיטה shemitah with the produce of שמיטה, shemitah, also
seemingly to be a דאורייתא. de-oraita.
So some of these are דאורייתא, de-oraita, some of these like the
gambling is דרבנן de-rabbanan because of אסמכתא קניא לא קניא. asmachta kanya
lo kanya. תוספות, Tosafot, or the gambling is a problem because of
the problem that they're not עוסקים ביישובו של עולם, oskim be-yishuvo shel
olam, that these are people that are like layabouts and they're not
doing productive labor and therefore there's a concern in all of these
cases that people are doing either sins דאורייתא de-oraita or דרבנן de-rabbanan
for monetary gain or just because they're not עוסקים ביישובו של עולם.
oskim be-yishuvo shel olam. These are people that don't understand the value
of money or are not engaged in a serious way in society
and all these types of people the concern is that they could
be bribed for their testimony. That's basically the common denominator here. Now
if they were doing an עבירה aveira that was an עבירה דאורייתא
aveira de-oraita and they were willingly doing it and they knew they
were transgressing and they were doing it for financial gain, then they
would be פסול לעדות דאורייתא pasul le-eidus de-oraita because of this אל
תשת ידך עם רשע להיות עד חמס, Al tashet yadcha im rasha
lihyot ed chamas, to be an עד חמס ed chamas and חמס
chamas understood to be about financial gain, so somebody who will עובר
over on a דאורייתא de-oraita knowingly and willingly for the sake of
financial gain is פסול דאורייתא. pasul de-oraita. But the assumption is that
everybody in our משנה Mishna is only פסול דרבנן. pasul de-rabbanan. Some
of the problems are only rabbinic problems like אסמכתא לא קניא asmachta
lo kanya or עוסקים ביישובו של עולם, oskim be-yishuvo shel olam,
and the
מלווה בריבית, malveh be-ribbit, תוספות Tosafot says either that's a case where
we're talking about a ריבית דרבנן ribbit de-rabbanan or it is a
case where the person has rationalized it and doesn't really think they're
willfully being it's, it's not a real דאורייתא, de-oraita, come on, it's
not really stealing, the guy's with a contract, he's agreeing to it
and therefore it's not that same type of willing knowing עבירה aveira
for the sake of monetary gain. Similarly שמיטה, shemitah, שמיטה shemitah nowadays
is דרבנן de-rabbanan so these cases are all assumed to be דרבנן
de-rabbanan but the invalid even if the עבירה aveira might be a
דאורייתא, de-oraita, but if it's a willing knowing transgression of an עבירה
דאורייתא aveira de-oraita then it's a פסול דאורייתא. pasul de-oraita. And רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda's statement that it's only when they don't have any
other gainful employment seems to be going only on the cases of
the gambling, about the משחק בקוביא misachek be-kubiya and מפריחי יונים. mafrichai
yonim. It doesn't really make sense in the other two cases. Okay,
so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with all of this.
אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, second wide line, אמר רב אלעזר
הלכה כרב יהודה. Amar Rav Elazar halacha ke-Rav Yehuda. We be like
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda at least in the cases that are אסמכתא
asmachta based and gambling based, that's not enough to invalidate somebody maybe
because we פוסקן pasken אסמכתא קניא asmachta kanya and therefore it has
to also be that they don't have any other gainful employment.
ואמר רבי אבהו אמר רב אלעזר כולן צריכין הכרזה בבית דין. Ve-amar
Rabbi Abahu Amar Rav Elazar kullan tzerichin hachraza be-veit din. Everybody mentioned
in the משנה, Mishna, anybody who's פסול דרבנן, pasul de-rabbanan, because it's
not פסול דאורייתא pasul de-oraita so the Rabbis can define the parameters
of when the פסול psul applies. So they're going to say that
that פסול psul only happens when there's an הכרזה בבית דין, hachraza
be-veit din, an announcement in בית דין Beit Din that this person
is פסול. pasul. And you can understand why that would be and
the גמרא Gemara will get to this in a minute, which is
if somebody let's say is a גנב gannav or גזלן gazlan and
really פסול דאורייתא pasul de-oraita and nobody knows about it and he
did some גזילה gezeila in January and then he testified on tons
of things February, March, April, May, June, finally in July there's testimony
that comes and says that in January he was a גזלן. gazlan.
All the things he testified on until now we retroactively find out
that all of that was invalid because he was פסול pasul as
an עד ed from the time that he became a גזלן, gazlan,
did an עבירה דאורייתא aveira de-oraita around money.
When it's only though a פסול דרבנן psul de-rabbanan we protect everybody
and we basically say that he's only going to be
פסול pasul once there is a הכרזה בבית דין, hachraza be-veit din,
once there's an announcement in בית דין. Beit Din. That's the teaching,
very important principle about פסולי עדות דרבנן. psulei eidus de-rabbanan. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, רועה. Roeh. How about the case of a shepherd, where we
said before that... that shepherds also, because they graze their sheep in
other lands, they're also considered פסול דרבנן. pasul derabanan. So what's the
story? פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא. Pligi bah Rav Acha veRavina. רב
אחא Rav Acha and רבינא Ravina debated. חד אמר בעיא הכרזה, Chad
amar beiya hachraza, it needs to be a public announcement, וחד אמר
לא בעיא הכרזה, vechad amar lo beiya hachraza, it doesn't. Now why
should a shepherd be different? So רש"י Rashi says because these other
people, it's not like it's publicly known. If some guy gambles, maybe
he gambles, he's in some gambling clubs and a few people know
about it, but it's not like
it's publicly known that this guy is a gambler or that this
guy sells שמיטה Shmita produce. But a רועה, ro'eh, that's your profession,
that's what you go and you do every day, it's publicly known.
So why would it need הכרזה? hachraza? Everybody knows he's a shepherd
and he's פסול. pasul. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא למאן דאמר לא בעיא הכרזה,
Bishlama lemand amar lo beiya hachraza, I understand that you'd say you
don't need הכרזה, hachraza, היינו דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב סתם
רועה פסול, Hainu de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav stam ro'eh pasul, that
even any shepherd is assumed to be פסול pasul unless you have
testimony that this guy totally keeps to his own fields. But without
that we just assume that any shepherd is invalid and grazes his
sheep in fields that are not his. So now you understand how
you could say that, that just out of without any other knowledge
you assume a shepherd is פסול pasul and that's consistent with the
idea of לא בעיא הכרזה lo beiya hachraza that you don't need
to announce his פסול psul in בית דין Beit Din because everybody
automatically just knows that he's פסול. pasul. אלא למאן דאמר בעיא הכרזה
מאי סתם רועה פסול? Ella lemand amar beiya hachraza mai stam ro'eh
pasul? But if you say that even a shepherd is only פסול
pasul only after the announcement in בית דין Beit Din has been
made, what's the point of saying that a סתם רועה stam ro'eh
is invalid? It's not true. No סתם רועה stam ro'eh is invalid.
A רועה ro'eh is only invalid once an announcement is made in
בית דין. Beit Din. So what's the meaning of סתם רועה פסול?
stam ro'eh pasul? So the
גמרא Gemara says דבסתמא מכריזן עליה. debistama machrizan alei. It's not that
we can just assume the populace that a רועה ro'eh is פסול.
pasul. It means when the בית דין Beit Din has to make
an announcement, they will make an announcement of every רועה ro'eh on
the presumption that they are פסול pasul unless it's a question of
burden of proof. Every רועה ro'eh has the assumption that they are
פסול pasul and they have the burden of proof to prove their
innocence. But the actual becoming פסול pasul still has to happen, it
doesn't happen automatically, that's not what סתם stam means, it means the
presumption בית דין Beit Din makes, but the פסול psul happens once
the announcement is made.
So that's the principle again that these people that are פסול דרבנן,
pasul derabanan, it's only with an announcement in בית דין. Beit Din.
Now, ההוא מתנה דהוו חתימי עליה תרי גזלנין. hahu matna de'avu chatmi
alei try gazlanin.
There was a certain gift that two גזלנין gazlanin were signed on
it as the עדים edim like a שטר shtar that was used
to transfer property. סבר רב פפא בר שמואל לאכשורי Savur Rav Pappa
bar Shmuel le'achshurei and he said, the שטר shtar is still valid.
Why? דלא אכריזן עלייהו de'lo achrizan alaihu because there was no public
pronouncement made by בית דין Beit Din so they're not invalid. So
presumably that would mean that they're not real גזלנין. gazlanin. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה רבא נהי דבעינן הכרזה בגזלן
דרבנן בגזלן דאורייתא מי בעינן הכרזה? Amlei Rava nehi dabeinan hachraza begazlan
derabanan begazlan de'oraisa mi beinan hachraza? So this is what I was
saying at the beginning but the punchline comes here in the גמרא.
Gemara. No, all the idea that you need הכרזה, hachraza, that is
when we're dealing with a דרבנן derabanan invalidity. So then
we can say we're only going to make it invalid once it's
been publicly pronounced and public information. But if somebody is פסול דאורייתא
pasul de'oraisa being a גזלן, gazlan, then that happens from the moment
that they became a גזלן gazlan and the הכרזה hachraza is not
necessary for that. We'll see a little bit more about how this
plays out by the case of
עד זומם. eid zomem. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. We'll
skip the סימן siman that's just a way a mnemonic to remember.
אמר רב נחמן אוכלי דבר אחר פסולין לעדות. Amar Rav Nachman ochlei
davar acher psulin le'eidus.
People that eat דבר אחר davar acher which usually refers to חזיר
chazir are invalid for עדות eidus purposes. Now we're going to see
that discussion in a minute. This is not particularly something that relates
to
money, it's an עבירה, aveira, you get מלקות malkus for, but it's
not really that relates to money. It is about physical pleasure and
enjoyment. Is that similar to things that relate to money? But anyway,
because the גמרא's Gemara going to make distinctions that would not make
any sense if we were talking about a real עבירה דאורייתא aveira
de'oraisa of eating חזיר, chazir, we'll see the distinctions in a minute.
רש"י Rashi says and תוספות Tosafot endorses this that this is just
a euphemism and what it really means is that they provide for
themselves, get sustained by צדקה tzedaka given by non-Jews. So that's probably
the דבר אחר, davar acher, the חזיר, chazir, the association of חזיר
chazir with non-Jews and so on. They eat it, they're sustained by
it, they receive public funds from non-Jews and this was seen as
something that was inappropriate to be done because it was a... חילול
השם chillul Hashem that non-Jews had to support them and not Jews.
The problem is that they needed money, but רש״י Rashi says that
it's like the idea of a רשע rasha of חמס. chamas. You're
willing to compromise your integrity, again this would be at a דרבנן
d'rabbanan level, you're not being עובר over on any דאורייתא d'oraiza thing,
but you're willing to do inappropriate things when you need money and
therefore we're concerned that you will give false testimony. Okay so that's
the חידוש. chiddush. Now but now the גמרא Gemara qualifies it. הני
מילי בפרהסיא אבל בצינעא לא. Hani mili be-farhesya aval be-tzina lo.
That's only if they accept these funds and it's a public matter.
If they do it in quiet and hush-hush, they're not really they're
sensitive to public norms and they're not really compromising things in a
serious way
and that doesn't invalidate them. ובפרהסיא נמי לא אמרינן אלא דאפשר ליה
לאיזוני בצינעא. U-be-farhesya nami lo amrinan ela de-efshar leih le-izonei be-tzina. And
even when we invalidate them because they do it in public, that's
only if they had a legitimate alternative at a way that they
could have been more private about it. And the fact that they
don't care again shows that these are people that when it comes
to monetary issues they can't really be trusted. וקמבזי נפשיה
בפרהסיא Ve-kamvazyei nafshai be-farhesya and they're willing to denigrate themselves by accepting
the money in public, so they will compromise for the sake of
monetary issues. אבל לא אפשר ליה, Aval lo efshar leih, but if
they had no alternative and the only way that they could get
צדקה tzedakah was by publicly accepting funds from the non-Jews,
חיותיה הוא. chiyyusei hu. Then people need to do something for a
living. When people need to accept צדקה tzedakah for basic necessities, that
does not mean people sometimes will do things as a compromise of
their dignity, that does not mean that they will compromise their integrity
and allow themselves to be bought off to give false testimony. Obviously
you're not going to jump from one to the next. Okay. אמר
רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, החשוד על העריות כשר לעדות. hachashad al
arayos kasher le-eidus. Now
now we get to a really important point. Even though we think
that people that will compromise their
הלכתי halakhic principles whether דאורייתא d'oraiza or דרבנן d'rabbanan for the sake
of monetary gain are considered invalid and if it's invalid דרבנן, d'rabbanan,
if it's a דאורייתא d'oraiza invalid דאורייתא. d'oraiza. But that's only when
it comes to money. If somebody is suspect of forbidden sexual acts,
they're only פסול דרבנן. pasul d'rabbanan.
Now why is that different than money? There's two things here that
could make it different. One is it's not that somebody
that
we actually saw do a forbidden sexual act. Somebody's just
suspected, he's always hanging out
around going into private with women and so on but nobody actually
knows for sure what he did.
In that type of a case
that's not enough to invalidate him. We don't have actually any concrete
action. All right but still
excuse me. So I think I might have said before that he
was that that he was פסול דרבנן. pasul d'rabbanan. I actually that
wasn't correct. Somebody who's חשוד על העריות chashud al arayos actually כשר.
kasher.
So anyway that is not a reason to invalidate him just because
he's חשוד. chashud. We don't actually know that he was עובר over
on anything. So we'll read it that way but then I want
to talk about go back and talk about the issue about עריות
arayos as compared to ממון. mamon. All right so חשוד על העריות
כשר לעדות. chashud al arayos kasher le-eidus. Just because somebody is suspect
that does not invalidate him. We don't know that they actually did
anything wrong. Being suspect is not enough to invalidate you.
אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, said רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, אנא
מרי אכיל ארבעין בכתפיה וכשר. ana marei achil arba'in be-katfei ve-kasher. Somebody
can be deserving of מלקות malkus and be כשר? kasher? Now why
is he deserving of מלקות? malkus? If he could be he really
did an איסור issur of עריות arayos but then he really should
be invalid and we'll see a whole discussion about that coming up
about עבירות aveiros that you get מלקות malkus for. But רש״י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafos both say that no what this means is the
idea that we give מלקות, malkus, מלקות דרבנן malkus d'rabbanan for somebody
that has a bad reputation around עריות. arayos. It's not the מלקות
דאורייתא. malkus d'oraiza. So
but remember this guy's just a חשוד. chashud. We don't know that
he transgressed. So therefore it's he's saying I don't get it. Somebody
who's such a bad guy that we give public lashes you're going
to say that he's not going to be פסול לעדות? pasul le-eidus?
So
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't give an answer to that. And the
answer is yes I will say it. It might be that he's
done stuff that's socially unacceptable, that he allowed himself to be חשוד
chashud and did certain actions but we don't know for sure and
that doesn't lead to us to suspect that he will go ahead
and give false testimony. Now here we also get to the point
not only that he's חשוד, chashud, but is there a difference between
עריות arayos and ממון? mamon? All the cases where somebody becomes פסול
pasul
that we've been dealing with is when he's doing it for monetary
gain and we're afraid that's רשע דחמס rasha de-chamas and we're afraid
that he's going to be paid off for false testimony. If somebody
does it for are other types of pleasure, you know, טרייף treif
food, he likes eating lobster, right, or עריות, arayos, does that mean
you know for some people that is a certain type of a
יצר, yetzer, a certain type of a desire that you might do
עבירות aveiros for, but as opposed to just plain money, money isn't
going to do it for this person. It's specifically עריות, arayos, it's
specifically something else. So it could be that that is a factor
as well that it's that because that we don't that it's only
about monetary things that somebody becomes invalid. We'll see again in a
minute things that you're deserving of real מלקות דאורייתא, malkus de'raisa, not
merely because of things that are just about you know pleasure. It
has to specifically be monetary. Anyway תוספות Tosafos has something of that
question, it could also be the idea that עריות arayos we understand
maybe there's a different way of saying what I just said, is
there's a particular יצר הרע yetzer hara for עריות arayos that doesn't
get transferred and can be assumed to apply to monetary issues. Okay,
so that seems to be like both of those things could be
at play here why the חשוד chashud on עריות arayos is כשר
kosher for עדות. edus. But this really shows that חז"ל Chazal understood
that just cause somebody you know compromises his principles or the הלכה
halacha in one area does not mean that it automatically transfers to
another.
Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. אמר רבא Amar
Rava said רבא Rava ומודה רב נחמן לענין עדות אשה שהוא פסול.
umodeh Rav Nachman le'inyan edus isha shehu pasul. But רב נחמן Rav
Nachman would agree that when it came to issues about testifying that
a woman's husband died for example or that a woman got divorced,
you couldn't trust this guy because that's the area he suspect in.
Okay, so we're not afraid that he'll be bought off to give
false testimony, but we are afraid that he'll testify that this woman's
husband died, maybe he wants to marry this woman.
So אמר Amar so so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבינא ואי
תימא רב פפא Amar Ravina ve'isayma Rav Pappa ולא אמרן אלא לאפוקה.
lo amran ela le'afuka. That's only if he's testifying regarding that this
woman is now a free woman, her husband died or divorced her.
אבל לעיולי לא, aval le'ayulei lo, but if he's testifying that the
woman got married, then he would be believed, we're not concerned that
he will falsely testify. פשיטא, peshita, isn't that obvious? No. מהו דתימא
האי ניחא ליה, ma d'seima hai nicha lei, maybe he wants the
woman to be married דכתיב מים גנובים ימתקו, d'chasiv mayim genuvim yimtaku,
stolen waters are sweet, maybe it's you know extra like it's particularly
exciting if he's having an affair not with a single woman but
with a married woman. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so it's
teaching us that we don't say that דכמה דקיימי הכא שכיחא ליה.
de'kama de'kaimi hacha shechicha lei. No, as long as she's single she's
more available to him and therefore we are not concerned that he's
going to testify falsely that she is married. Okay what's interesting here
is that this חשוד chashud on עריות arayos is a more circumstantial
concern, the specific area when it comes specific type about a woman
getting divorced or getting widowed, we don't believe him cause there we
actually are concerned about his honesty, but there's no formal invalidity. All
the other types of things we just say black and white this
person is פסול, pasul, you know when it's monetary issues, this person
it's only specifically on the areas that he is suspect about. Okay.
ואמר רב נחמן ve'amar Rav Nachman and said רב נחמן Rav Nachman
גנב ניסן וגנב תשרי לא שמיה גנב. ganav Nissan ve'ganav Tishrei lo
shemei ganav. If somebody steals in ניסן Nissan or תשרי, Tishrei, which
are the times you know where you are either harvesting the wheat
or in ניסן Nissan you know or תשרי Tishrei when you're gathering
the stuff in. So if you have a sharecropper that's helping himself
to a little food during those major
agricultural times, then that does not invalidate somebody. This gets to the
principle about that even if somebody's doing an איסור דאורייתא, issur de'oraisa,
stealing food that belongs to the owner of the field, but if
they have their whole rationalization then you know that doesn't mean that
they're really going to willingly falsely testify for money. You know they
did a experiment where they put like a bottle of Coke out
on the table in a break room in different offices and people
would just help themselves to it. It had no name on it,
they would just help themselves to it. They put like a dollar
bill out there and you know people wouldn't take it cause one
it's like I'm just taking a drink of some I'm just having
soda, it doesn't feel as much like you're stealing you know than
when you take money that doesn't belong to you. So similar idea
here and therefore that does not make the person invalid to testify.
הני מילי באריסא, hanei milei be'arisa, now that's only if you're dealing
with a sharecropper since a sharecropper gets a portion of the harvest
so they already have a right to the food, they take a
little extra doesn't really feel like stealing. ודבר מועט, ve'davar muat, and
if it's small amount. ובדבר שנגמרה מלאכתו, u'vedavar shenigmeru melachto, and when
all of the processing is done and then you feel like oh
look I finished the job I can help myself to a few
extra grapes or whatever it is.
אכרי דרב זביד, ichrei de'Rav Zvid, the tenant farmer, this is not
a sharecropper, this is somebody who's paid. of רב זביד Rav Zvid
חד גנב קבא דשערי, chad ganav kava d'sari, one stole a measure
of barley ופסליה u'paslei and he invalidated him, וחד גנב קיבורא דאהיני
v'chad ganav kibura d'ahini and one stole like a cluster of grapes
ופסליה u'paslei and he invalidated him. It sounds like from רש״י Rashi
that the reason here is is because they were not sharecroppers, they
were paid laborers, so therefore the rationalization logic does not apply as
to the same degree. הנהו קבוראי דקברי נפשא ביום טוב ראשון של
שבועות. Hanu k'vurai d'kavri nasha b'yom tov rishon shel Shavuot. There were
some gravediggers that would
bury a corpse on the first day of שבועות Shavuot and you're
not allowed to do that. You have to wait till the second
day of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So שמתינהו רב פפא, shamteinu Rav
Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa put them in חרם cherem ופסלינהו
לעדות u'paslinu l'eidus and he made them פסול לעדות. posul l'eidus. Why?
Because again, they did an עבירה aveira for the sake of monetary
gain. They were being paid to do the job to bury the
person. So we're afraid now that they will testify falsely.
ואכשרינהו רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, V'achshirinu Rav Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua,
and רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua said
no they're still כשר. kosher. אמר ליה רב פפא, Amar lei Rav
Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa said ורשעים נינהו, v'resha'im ninhu, but
they're wicked
because they compromised, they did this עבירה aveira for money. No, סברי
מצוה קא עבדי, savri mitzvah ka avdi, again they're rationalizing it, they're
saying to themselves it's not an עבירה, aveira, we're doing, we're burying
someone. So therefore you know then you can't rationalize testifying falsely. So
this they rationalized. והא קא משמתינן להו, V'ha ka meshamteinu lehu, but
he says but I put them in חרם. cherem. So and presumably
then they did it next time, they know they're doing something wrong
and they're willingly violating. No, סברי כפרה קא עבדי לן רבנן. savri
kapara ka avdi lan rabbanan. They say what we're doing is allowed,
it's a מצוה, mitzvah, it's a good thing and okay it broke
יום טוב Yom Tov but but it was the right thing to
do, but because it broke יום טוב Yom Tov by putting us
in חרם cherem that sort of is a כפרה kapara for that,
but nevertheless it was the right thing to do. So people have
ways of rationalizing things and when that's happening then if they're not
פסול דאורייתא posul d'Oraita or that means that they're not פסול דאורייתא
posul d'Oraita because the פסול דאורייתא psul d'Oraita of רשע דחמס rasha
d'chamas is you have to be doing something for monetary gain that's
an עבירה דאורייתא aveira d'Oraita to be פסול דאורייתא posul d'Oraita an
עבירה דרבנן aveira d'Rabbanan to be פסול דרבנן posul d'Rabbanan and do
it willingly and knowingly and without a rationalization. Okay, איתמר. itmar. Now
it was taught top of כז עמוד א. chaf zayin amud aleph.
עדים זוממים. eid zomem. This is a debate in בבא קמא Bava
Kamma and it's also said here. If somebody is a found to
be an עד זומם, eid zomem, they testified and then two עדים
eidim came and said two people testified, two came and said how
can you testify about that? You were with us on such and
such a date and the תורה Torah says that you believe the
second group of witnesses and the first one are assumed to be
the liars and ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם, v'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, you
do what they were trying to do to the other person. So
when do they become invalid? אביי אמר למפרע הוא נפסל. Abaye amar
l'mafrei'a hu nifsal. They become invalid retroactively from the moment they testified
falsely. That's when they did this עבירה aveira and it's an עבירה
aveira of falsely testifying. So obvious so that invalidates them to ever
to serve as witnesses. ורבא אמר v'Rava amar no, מכאן ולהבא הוא
נפסל. mikan u'l'haba hu nifsal. They only become invalidated from the time
that the מזימים mazzimim came, from the time that the other witnesses
came and said back in January when they testified they were liars.
If those people came in March, these עדים זוממים eidim zomemim are
only invalid from March on, even though they gave their first false
testimony back in January. Now אביי אמר למפרע הוא נפסל, Abaye amar
l'mafrei'a hu nifsal, retroactive. מעידנא דסהיד רשיעא הוא. M'idna d'sahid rasha hu.
From the moment that they gave false testimony in January, they were
רשעים. resha'im. That's a classic case of somebody who's an invalid witness,
somebody who has already proven to have testified falsely. והתורה אמרה, V'haTorah
amra, the תורה Torah said אל תשת ידך עם רשע, al tashet
yadcha im rasha, do not put your hand like raise up your
hand with the wicked, אל תשת להיות עד חמס al tashet l'hiyot
eid chamas to be a false witness. אל תשת רשע עד, Al
tashet rasha eid, don't put your hand, don't let a רשע rasha
sort of raise his hand to be a witness. So a רשע
rasha cannot be a witness and they were
רשעים. resha'im. So that's that. רבא אמר מכאן ולהבא הוא נפסל. Rava
amar mikan u'l'haba hu nifsal. No, only going forward. Why? עדים זוממים
חידוש הוא Eid zomem chiddush hu because the whole idea that they're
invalid is a חידוש chiddush is a innovation of the תורה. Torah.
Why is it an innovation of the תורה? Torah? מאי חזית דסמכת
אהני סמוך אהני. Mai chazei samchat hani smat hani. Why do you
rely on the second witnesses that came in March to say the
first ones were invalid? Maybe the first ones are valid and the
second ones are lying? It's two against two. So the תורה Torah
has told you you go by the second ones when they say
עמנו הייתם אותו היום, imanu hayitem oto hayom, you were with us
on that day. Okay, that's a חידוש chiddush of the תורה. Torah.
ואין לך בו אלא משעת חידושו ואילך. V'ein lacha bo ela misha'at
chiddusho v'eilach. If the תורה's Torah going to innovate that these witnesses
are invalid, then all I know is from the time of the
innovation and onwards. now is, and there's no rational reason, I'm not
going to say retroactively I know for sure that they lied back
in January. What I'm going to say is as of March when
the תורה Torah gave them the status of עדים זוממים eidim zomemim
and said based on the fact that these second witnesses come you
treat the first witnesses as the false witnesses, okay, that doesn't clarify
for me as a fact that they testified falsely back in January.
That just gives them the status of עדים זוממים eidim zomemim and
therefore their invalidity only starts from that point on. That's מכאן ולהבא.
mikan u'lehabo. So איכא דאמרי ika d'amri others say רבא נמי כוותיה
דאביי סבירא ליה, Rava nammi k'vasei d'Abaye svira lei, רבא Rava really
in principle agrees to אביי Abaye that they retroactively are invalid.
ומאי טעמא קאמר מכאן ולהבא? u'mai ta'ama ka'amar mikan u'lehabo? Why does
he say they only become invalid from this point onward in March
when the זוממים zomemim come? משום פסידא דלקוחות mishum pseida d'lakuchos because
we're concerned about all the things the witnesses could have testified on
between January and March, all the various documents and so on that
they were as far as anybody knew totally כשר kosher witnesses. The
court accepted their testimony in January so people will continue to use
them, February, March, etc. So now all those people that used them
are going to now have all their documents invalidated. So therefore rabbinically
we're going to keep those documents okay and say that their invalidity
only starts when it is known when these זוממים zomemim come in
March. It's sort of similar to the idea before about הכרזה hachraza
about a public announcement in בית דין. Beis Din. This isn't about
a public proclamation but it still is we're going to hold off
even though they were invalid earlier if nobody could know it and
their testimony was ממש mamash accepted by the court already in January
then their invalidity rabbinically will not begin until when it becomes publicly
known that they are invalid. Not a proclamation of the court but
when it becomes verified you know clarified that they are invalid.
Okay. מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What's the difference between the two reasons
of רבא, Rava, whether it is because
it's a חידוש chiddush or whether it's because of protecting innocent לקוחות,
lakuchos, purchasers who are going to use their
testimony? איכא בינייהו דאסהידו בי תרי בחד. ika beinaihu d'ashidu bei trei
bechad. So one place would be that let's say as opposed to
being two against two it was two against one. So ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon in January said somebody borrowed a hundred dollars and
לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda come in March and they don't say
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon were both with us, they say ראובן
Reuven was with us. So since they're only talking about ראובן Reuven
it's two against one and therefore two against one they are believed
okay, because שמעון Shimon isn't testifying about ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon are testifying about what they saw. So in that case
there's no חידוש chiddush so it would be
למפרע lemifrei retroactive if the reason was just because it was a
חידוש chiddush of the תורה. Torah. If however it's to protect the
innocent לקוחות lakuchos purchasers who used these witnesses then even in such
a case it would only be from March on. אי
נמי דפסלינהו בגזלנותא, ei nami d'paslinhu begazlanusa, or that in March those
witnesses came and they didn't say ראובן Reuven was with us on
that day, they said ראובן Reuven was a גזלן. gazlan. We know
that ראובן Reuven was a גזלן gazlan back in January. Has nothing
to do with עדים זוממים eidim zomemim anymore. It's a little funny,
we're leaving the discussion of עדים זוממים eidim zomemim okay, but in
March they're not saying that they were עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim, they're
saying that so-and-so was a גזלן. gazlan. If the concern is that
עדים זוממים eidim zomemim is a חידוש, chiddush, well this isn't עדים
זוממים eidim zomemim so the פסול psul would start back in January.
If there's a general principle that you need to protect the innocent
לקוחות lakuchos so then even in this case it would only begin
in March and that would make that this then very close. It's
interesting, before רבא Rava said when it's a case of a גזלן
gazlan we don't need a הכרזה hachraza in בית דין Beis Din
and
here the גמרא Gemara is saying according to one reading of רבא
Rava that in a case of a גזלן gazlan the פסול psul
would wait at least maybe not till הכרזה hachraza but at least
till it was clarified in בית דין Beis Din that this person
actually was a גזלן. gazlan. Okay. מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What's the
difference between the two reasons of רבא? Rava? ואמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי
עבד רב פפי עובדא כוותיה דרבא. v'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah mi-Diphti avad Rav
Pappi uvda k'vasei d'Rava. רבי ירמיה מדיפתי Rabbi Yirmiyah mi-Diphti says
רב פפי Rav Pappi acted like רבא Rava that it was only
פסול pasul from the time that the second witnesses came and not
going back, not retroactively. מר בר רב אשי אמר הלכתא כוותיה דאביי,
Mar bar Rav Ashi amar hilchata k'vasei d'Abaye, but מר בר רב
אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says we go like אביי Abaye and
והלכתא והלכתא כוותיה דאביי ביע"ל קג"ם v'hilchata v'hilchata k'vasei d'Abaye b'YA'AL KAGAM
and we rule like אביי Abaye in יע"ל קג"ם YA'AL KAGAM and
this is one of them. יע"ל קג"ם, YA'AL KAGAM, י yod is
יאוש שלא מדעת, yeush shelo mada'as,
ע ayin is עדים זוממים eidim zomemim exactly this question למפרע מכאן
ולהבא. lemifrei mikan u'lehabo. So we rule like אביי Abaye that עדים
זוממים eidim zomemim is למפרע lemifrei and the same would be true
about
a גזלן. gazlan. protecting of
לקוחות, lakuchos, you know, that רבא Rava was saying. So that's עדים
זוממים למפרע הוא נפסל. edim zomemim lemafrea hu nifsal. The רש"י Rashi
gives the rest, the למד lamed is לחי העומד מאליו, lechi ha'omed
me'elav, the קוף kuf is קידושין שלא נמסרו לביאה, kiddushin shelo nimseru
l'viah, the גימל gimmel is גילוי דעת בגיטין, gilluy da'as b'gittin, and
the מם mem is מומר אוכל נבילות להכעיס mumar ochel neveilos l'hach'is
which we're going to get to so I'm not going to explain
all of those. But we will get to the מם. mem. We
have two right, two of those six right side by side here
in this גמרא. Gemara.
Now, so let's get to the מם. mem. מומר אוכל נבילות לתיאבון.
mumar ochel neveilos l'te'avon. If somebody is a, is a regular violator
who eats נבילה neveila just because of desire, appetite, he's not doing
it להכעיס, l'hach'is, he's doing it because of his יצר הרע. yeitzer
hara. דברי הכל פסול. divrei hakol pasul. Everybody agrees that he's invalid
to be a test, to testify. Why? So this gets back to
the question I raised before. Is it because if you'll do an
עבירה aveira for pleasure, you'll also do an עבירה aveira for money?
So the same way when you do things, you know, we're including
things that are about הנאה hana'ah like food, sex, etc. in the
רשע דחמס rasha d'chamas or no, this is specifically נבילה. neveila. It
doesn't say lobster, it doesn't say חזיר. chazir. נבילה neveila is the
exact same meat as the kosher meat, you're not doing it because
it tastes better. The only reason somebody would eat נבילה neveila over
kosher meat is because it's cheaper. So in the end this really
is a monetary issue. So if you're buying the cheaper טרייף treif
meat, then you're רשע דחמס. rasha d'chamas. We're afraid that you'll compromise
yourself for money. However,
that's if you do it, I just lost my place, ah, להכעיס.
l'hach'is. If somebody however eats נבילה neveila not because of money, because
he's just angry at God, he does it in spite. So now
normally a מומר להכעיס mumar l'hach'is is much worse than a מומר
לתיאבון. mumar l'te'avon. מומר להכעיס mumar l'hach'is is really doing it for,
you know, theological reasons. It's not just יצר הרע yeitzer hara of
appetite. But nevertheless when it comes to עדות eidus he might be
better because he doesn't compromise his principles for money. Okay, and just
because he's angry at God and going to be doing this to
spite doesn't mean he'll testify falsely against another person for money. Who,
money, who cares about money?
Okay. אביי אמר פסול. Abaye amar pasul. What אביי Abaye says nevertheless
he's invalid. Why? So it could have to be like you do
one עבירה aveira you'll do another עבירה aveira similar to the ideas
before about being חשוד. chashud. You know, like, but the, the general
understanding is not that way. The general understanding is that this is
a formal פסול. psul. If you do an עבירה aveira that you're
deserving to get lashes for, מלקות, malkus, then anybody who's obligated in
מלקות malkus is deserving of מלקות malkus is called a רשע. rasha.
והרשיעו את הרשע. v'hirshiu es harasha. So that formally defines you as
a רשע. rasha. It doesn't have to do with your compromised integrity
and being able to be bought off. You did something, you get
lashes for it, you're a רשע. rasha. That's what אביי Abaye says.
And this by the way is the מם, mem, מומר אוכל נבילות
להכעיס, mumar ochel neveilos l'hach'is, that we rule like אביי. Abaye. So
I'll just pause here or we'll just read רבא. Rava. רבא אמר
כשר. Rava amar kasher. רבא Rava says it's כשר. kasher. אביי אמר
פסול דהוה ליה רשע. Abaye amar pasul d'hava lei rasha. By doing
an עבירה aveira that you're חייב מלקות chayav malkus you're a רשע.
rasha. ורחמנא אמר אל תשת רשע עד. v'rachmana amar al tashes rasha
eid. A רשע rasha cannot be a witness. ורבא אמר כשר רשע
דחמס בעינן. v'Rava amar kasher rasha d'chamas bayinan. No, it's only somebody
who does something with money. Somebody who סתם stam does עבירות aveiros
we're not afraid they'll testify falsely. And I don't agree to you
אביי Abaye that there's a formal category called רשע rasha when you
do something that you're deserving of מלקות. malkus. We rule like אביי
Abaye and and הלכתא hilchasa witnesses could be פסול pasul for two
reasons: a רשע דחמס, rasha d'chamas, somebody who compromises themselves for monetary
reasons and those could even be things that are not דאורייתא d'oraisa
but without but only when they're compromising themselves without a rationalization. Which
the rationalization is different as we've seen before. And there's a רשע
rasha of when you're חייב מלקות chayav malkus and that's just a
formal רשע, rasha, and that's another פסול. psul. That's how אביי Abaye
rules.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll challenge you on this. אל תשת רשע עד. al
tashes rasha eid. So we have a ברייתא, braisa, אל תשת ידך
עם רשע להיות עד חמס, al tashes yadecha im rasha l'hiyos eid
chamas, so the key words for us is a רשע rasha cannot
be a witness and also the word of חמס, chamas, אל תשת
חמס עד. al tashes chamas eid. And somebody for חמס. chamas. So
that's already sounding like אביי Abaye there are two categories, רשע rasha
and חמס. chamas. So,
and now the ברייתא braisa explains. אלו גזלנים ומלוים בשבועות. elu gazlanim
u'malvim b'shvuos.
These are people that are thieves and also people that violate oaths.
So מאי לאו mai lav because it says שבועות shvuos in the
plural, אחד שבועת שוא ואחד שבועת ממון, echad shvuas shav v'echad shvuas
mamon, whether it is an oath that you're falsely testifying to save
yourself money, you know, somebody thinks you borrowed and you take an
oath that you didn't borrow, or you just make a false oath,
you swear on gold that it's silver or on you know an
animal that it's a, that it's a chair or something silly like
that. So and therefore it's just an עבירה aveira but it's not
about money, and So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, אידי ואידי שבועת
ממון. Lo, idi ve'idi shvu'as mamon. No,
שבועות shvuos does not mean two types, it all talking about oaths
that are done in order to say in order to steal money
or to deny money that you're owed, ומה שבועות שבועות דממון. u'mah
shvuos shvuos damamon. שבועות Shvuos just means any types of שבועות shvuos
you can make, but it doesn't I mean it's the type שבועות
shvuos you would make for monetary purposes. It doesn't mean two categories
of שבועות. shvuos. Okay, so we're going to claim that again we're
only dealing in the money category. מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you again.
אל תשת רשע עד. Al teshes rasha ed.
אל תשת חמס עד. Al teshes chamas ed. Again a ברייתא Baraisa
that starts seemingly to define two categories, רשע Rasha and חמס, Chamas,
seems to support אביי. Abaye. אלו גזלנים ומלווי ריבית. Eilu gazlanim u'malvei
ribis. But the examples it gives are,
even though it mentioned both of those, are only monetary issues. Thieves
and people that lend with ריבית. ribis. תיובתא דאביי תיובתא. Tyufta d'Abaye
tyufta. That is a complete contradiction to אביי, Abaye, that shows that
the entire category is limited to money. Now you already know the
end of the story is that the that we פסקן pasken like,
you know, the מ mem of מומר אוכל להכעיס mumar ochel lehachis
is like אביי. Abaye. So the story isn't over yet. נימא כתנאי.
Nima k'tannai. Let's say that this is the debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
עד זומם פסול לכל התורה כולה דברי רבי מאיר. Ed zomem pasul
l'chol haTorah kullah divrei Rabbi Meir. So somebody is found as an
עד זומם, ed zomem, they're פסול pasul for all testimonies. We're no
longer wondering about whether it's retroactive or מכאן ולהבא, mikan u'lehabah, but
the scope, they're פסול pasul for everything. רבי יוסי אומר במה דברים
אמורים שזממו בדיני נפשות. Rabbi Yossi omer bameh devarim amurim she'zimmu b'dinei
nefashos. When is that true? If they were found עדים זוממים edim
zomemim with a case about somebody's life. You wonder how they're not
dead then, but okay, for whatever reason we didn't do get around
to the כאשר זמם, ka'asher zamam, maybe חס ושלום chas v'shalom the
person actually was killed.
אבל הוזממו בדיני ממונות, Aval huzmmu b'dinei mamonos, but if they were
found to be false witnesses just for monetary purposes, כשר לדיני נפשות.
kasher l'dinei nefashos. Then they can testify for life and death cases.
Basically his thinking is just because somebody is willing to compromise their
principles for hurting somebody in the monetary realm and testify falsely, we
can't assume that they will testify falsely when it comes to actually
somebody's life. Makes sense. Okay, so נימא אביי כרבי מאיר ורבא כרבי
יוסי. nima Abaye k'Rabbi Meir v'Rava k'Rabbi Yossi. Maybe the debate of
אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava line up with רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי. Rabbi
Meir v'Rabbi Yossi. How does that play out? אביי כרבי מאיר דאמרינן
מחומרא לקולא. Abaye k'Rabbi Meir d'amrinan mechumra l'kulla. אביי Abaye goes like
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that even if somebody did something more light,
they just testified against somebody in a monetary realm, they're invalid for
something more heavy. They can't testify against the person in a life
and death case. Why? If you're just concerned about practical considerations, you
know, just because he did it for money, he did to hurt
somebody with money, he's not going to hurt somebody when it comes
to their life. So it sounds like like it's not just about
practical considerations. It's a formal invalidity. So you're a false witness, you've
been proven a false witness, you're פסול pasul across the board. You're
a רשע, rasha, you're פסול pasul across the board. I don't care
if the logic is there or not there. That sounds like אביי.
Abaye. ורבא דאמר כרבי יוסי. V'Rava d'amar k'Rabbi Yossi. And רבא Rava
says like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, דאמרינן מחומרא לקולא אמרינן מקולא לחומרא
לא אמרינן. d'amrinan mechumra l'kulla amrinan mikulla l'chumra lo amrinan. We go
from weighty to light, not light to weighty. Meaning there's no formal
invalidity. We only do it based on: is there a logic to
why because you if you did this wrong, you'll also do that
wrong. And that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says. If you testified
falsely to get somebody killed, you'll certainly we're concerned you'll testify falsely
for money. But just because you testified falsely to hurt somebody in
monetary matters, doesn't mean you'll testify for them in to get them
killed. So that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi approach is: is there a
logical reason to assume because you did this X here, you'll also
testify falsely over there. And that's and but not any formal invalidity.
And the same is true by רבא. Rava. Okay? So רבא Rava
says just because you were willing to eat נבילה להכעיס, neveilah lehachis,
that doesn't translate into your into your willingness to testify falsely.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues to spell this out.
לא,
אליבא דרבי יוסי כולי עלמא לא פליגי. Lo, aliba d'Rabbi Yossi kuli
alma lo pligi. When it comes to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, clearly
everybody agrees that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi does not work with אביי.
Abaye. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi does not have a formal invalidity from
money
to from testifying life and death you're invalid to if you lie,
to testify about money, but if you testified about money and you
lied, you're still valid to testify about life and death. Everybody agrees
that is not an אביי Abaye approach because that is not a
categorical invalidity. It's based on a practical concern.
כי פליגי אליבא דרבי מאיר. Ki pligi aliba d'Rabbi Meir. The debate
of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava is whether רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
clearly goes like אביי Abaye or could רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir even
go like רבא. Rava. כי פליגי אליבא דרבי מאיר. Ki pligi aliba
d'Rabbi Meir. I lost my place, oh. אביי כרבי מאיר. Abaye k'Rabbi
Meir. אביי Abaye says that I'm I'm רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says if you're invalid when you testify against... somebody
by monetary, you're also invalid about life and death. Why? It's a
formal invalidity, it's a categorical פסול, psul, and the same would be
true about אוכל נבילות להכעיס. ochel neveilos l'hachis. Okay, it's not about
concerns, it's about a formal invalidity. ורבא, v'Rava, but רבא Rava would
say no, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם אלא לגבי עדים
זוממים דממונא דמרע לשמיא ומרע לבריות. ad kan lo ka'amar Rebbe Meir
hasam ela l'gabbei eidim zomemim d'mammona d'mara l'shamaya u'mara l'briyos. רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir might have a category, but that category at least it's
things that are similar, okay, because you testified falsely against somebody, even
though it was only monetary, not only were you sinning to God,
you were sinning against this person. So therefore, I will also invalidate
you about life and death cases, but at least that's the same
category. You testified falsely, you're going to be invalid to testify in
all cases. Okay, אבל הכא, aval hacha, but the case of מומר
אוכל נבילות להכעיס, mumar ochel neveilos l'hachis, דמרע לשמיא ואינו מרע לבריות,
d'mara l'shamaya v'eino mara l'briyos, it's only a sin against God, you're
not hurting anybody, that's a different category, and just because you did
those עבירות aveiros that does not invalidate you to testify, לא, lo,
that would not invalidate you. So that makes a lot of sense.
You could take an approach of a practical concern, which is like
עד חמס, eid chamas, and you know, and therefore you'll go from
נפשות nefashos to ממון mammon but not ממון mammon to נפשות. nefashos.
And even if you take a categorical thing, it could be okay,
once you are a, you know, you do a, you hurt somebody
for money, I'll just say you're never כשר kosher for any testimony,
but I'm not going to jump from a purely, you know,
ritualistic type of בין אדם למקום bein adam l'makom עבירה aveira to
invalidate you as an עד. eid. There's no logic there. So, and
that's a very reasonable position. But now let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. והלכתא v'hilchasa and the הלכה halacha is, והלכתא כוותיה דאביי.
v'hilchasa k'vosei d'Abaye.
We rule like אביי, Abaye, it's one of the יעל קגם. y'al
k'gam. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say והא אותיב,
v'ha osiv, one minute, besides what I just said, which is that
רבא's Rava position has a lot of logic to it, you know,
we said תיובתא דאביי תיובתא, tiyufta d'Abaye tiyufta, he's been contradicted,
the list only said גזלנים ומלוי בריבית. gazlanim u'malvei b'ribbis. So the
גמרא Gemara says ההיא רבי יוסי היא, hahi Rebbe Yossi hi, that's
going like רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yossi. אביי Abaye will still claim רבי
יוסי Rebbe Yossi is the one that has practical concerns. רבי מאיר's
Rebbe Meir categorical, and I would say categorical across the board. Even
מומר אוכל נבילות, mumar ochel neveilos, even though it's only בין אדם
למקום, bein adam l'makom, it still invalidates you, you're a רשע, rasha,
you did an עבירה aveira that you're חייב מלקות. chayav malkos. I
go like רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. So the ברייתא braisa that was
practical and said מלוי בריבית וגזלנים, malvei b'ribbis v'gazlanim, that was רבי
יוסי, Rebbe Yossi, but I'm a רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir man. So
the גמרא, Gemara,
excuse me, I got that reversed, והא
אותיב ההיא רבי יוסי היא, v'ha osiv hahi Rebbe Yossi hi, that
was רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yossi, okay, that ברייתא, braisa,
but I go like רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. ותהוי נמי רבי יוסי,
u's'havi nami Rebbe Yossi, okay, but once you're conceding that that's רבי
יוסי Rebbe Yossi and אביי Abaye is saying I side with רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir, that's still not going to get you to פסקן
pasken like אביי. Abaye. רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי הלכה כרבי יוסי. Rebbe
Meir u'Rebbe Yossi halacha k'Rebbe Yossi. Even if אביי Abaye says I
have רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir to go like me, even though that's
debatable, we still generally rule like רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi over רבי
מאיר. Rebbe Meir. So it doesn't make any sense why we should
be going like אביי. Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני
התם דסתם לן תנא כרבי מאיר. shani hasam d'stam lan tanna k'Rebbe
Meir. No, we have a סתם משנה stam mishna like רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir that says that that indicates that the category of the
פסול עדות psul eidus is categorical like אביי. Abaye. And that's why
we rule like אביי. Abaye. Okay, what is the סתם משנה? stam
mishna? והיכא סתם לן? v'heicha stam lan? Where do we have the
סתם משנה? stam mishna? כי הא דבר חמא. ki ha d'Bar Chama.
The following case, that there's this guy called בר חמא, Bar Chama,
קטל נפשא, ktal nafsha, he murdered somebody. אמר ליה ריש גלותא לרב
אבא, amar leh Reish Galusa l'Rav Abba, so the ריש גלותא, Reish
Galusa, the, you know, Jewish head of the Babylonian community, said to
רב אבא בר יעקב, Rav Abba Bar Yaakov, פוק עיין בה, puk
ayyein bah, go and investigate this case. אי וודאי קטל, ei vaddai
ktal, and if he definitely killed somebody, ליחמיו ליה לעיניה, lichmiyu leh
l'einei, blind his eyes. As רש״י Rashi says, they didn't have the
power necessary to execute, but you know, this happened throughout history, the
Jews had, were given degrees of power over their community, and they
sometimes used physical force. So that's what you should do to him
if he's genuinely found to have killed somebody. Okay,
אתו תרי סהדי, asu terei sahadi, two witnesses came. אסהידו ביה דבוודאי
קטל, ashidu beh d'b'vaddai ktal, and they testified, yes, we saw him
kill somebody.
אזיל איהו, azil ihu, so then this person, this accused, went. אתו
תרי סהדי, asu terei sahadi, and he brought two witnesses. אסהידו ביה
בחד מהני, ashidu beh b'chad mehani,
and they testified against one of them. חד אמר קמאי דידי גנב
קבא דחומשא וחד אמר קמאי דידי גנב
קטא דבורטיא. chad amar kamai didi ganav kava d'chumsha v'chad amar kamai
didi ganav kata d'vortia. So one said one of these, you know,
that this guy stole, they both testified about one of the witnesses
that
he was
פסול. psul. stole
a handle of
an, of a spear. Okay? So they testified that one of the
guys was a גזלן gazlan and therefore invalid.
And therefore the witnesses are invalid and therefore the guy you can't
prove that the guy was a murderer. אמר ליה Amar lei מאי
דעתך? mai da'atach? Says then the rabbi who was adjudicating, who was
that again? That was רב אבא בר יעקב Rav Abba bar Yaakov
said to I guess the accused. What's your thinking? כרבי מאיר? ke'Rabbi
Meir? That we would go like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Because remember
this is exactly the רבי מאיר רבי יוסי. Rabbi Meir Rabbi Yossi.
It's not the מומר אוכל נבילות mumar ochel nevelos case. So here
they're claiming that he was פסול pasul because of a monetary thing.
He was willing to do an עבירה aveira for money. Okay? But
here it's a capital case. So according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
even if somebody is suspect for monetary issues, he's not going to
be suspect to be falsely testifying in a capital case. So he
said to the accused, what, you think we go like רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? That somebody who's a גזלן gazlan can't be a witness
for a capital case? רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי הלכה כרבי יוסי. Rabbi
Meir ve'Rabbi Yossi halacha ke'Rabbi Yossi. No, we go like רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי הא אמר הואיל ומדיני ממונות כשר לדיני נפשות.
Rabbi Yossi ha amar ho'il umidinei mamonos kosher ledinei nefashos. And רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says that even if somebody is established to be
a false witness for monetary matters, they're still כשר kosher to be
a witness in capital cases. Okay? So you can't invalidate this witness
against you. אמר ליה רב פפי, Amar lei Rav Pappi, so רב
פפי Rav Pappi said to him, הני מילי היכא דלא סתם לן
תנא כרבי מאיר. hani mili heicha dela stam lan tanna ke'Rabbi Meir.
That's only true that we go like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi if
there isn't a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
הכא סתם לן תנא כרבי מאיר. hacha stam lan tanna ke'Rabbi Meir.
Here we have a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So now we have a very fascinating practical case, but we're
back to the claim that there's a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. What is it? מאי היא? mai hi? ממאי?
mimai? אילימא מהא דתנן, Ilima me'ha detnan, כל הראוי לדון דיני נפשות
ראוי לדון דיני ממונות. kol hara'ui ladun dinei nefashos ra'ui ladun dinei
mamonos. Anybody that can be a judge, and now we're going to
assume judge is the same as witness, in capital cases can be
a judge in monetary cases. So מני? mani? Who's this going like?
אילימא רבי יוסי, Ilima Rabbi Yossi, if it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
הא איכא עד זומם דממונא דכשר לדיני נפשות ופסול לדיני ממונות. ha
ika ed zomem demamona de'kosher ledinei nefashos u'pasul ledinei mamonos. No, I'll
give you somebody. Somebody who testified falsely in monetary cases and that
type of a person for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi can't testify in
monetary, but can testify in capital. And presumably the same would be
true about being a דיין. dayan. It's pretty funny that somebody who
actually was a false witness, the גמרא Gemara is assuming an equation
here, but somebody who was a false witness by monetary issues could
be a דיין dayan on a capital case. So it's a little
funny the way the גמרא Gemara is glossing over the difference between
דיין dayan and עד. ed. But okay. Anyway, but for רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi
somebody could be
פסול pasul for
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos and כשר kosher for
דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. אלא לאו רבי מאיר היא? Ela lav Rabbi
Meir hi? It must be רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And there you
have a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Because
for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi you could be פסול pasul for ממונא
mamona and כשר kosher for נפשות. nefashos. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, ממאי? mimai? Who tells you that? דילמא בפסולי יוחסין קאי. dilma
be'psulei yuchsin kai. Maybe we're dealing with people that their פסול psul
has nothing to do
with sins or with false testimony. It has to do with their
יוחסין, yuchsin, with
their family. And we'll see about that later, that there's a high
level of יוחסין yuchsin required for somebody to be a דיין dayan
on a capital case. דאי לא תימא הכי, de'ei lo teima hachi,
because if you don't say that, סיפא דקתני, seifa de'katani, the end
of that משנה Mishnah teaches, יש ראוי לדון דיני ממונות ואין ראוי
לדון דיני נפשות. yesh ra'ui ladun dinei mamonos ve'ein ra'ui ladun dinei
nefashos. That there are people that can be כשר kosher for monetary
cases and not כשר kosher for capital cases. Okay. So if we're
dealing with cases of יוחסין, yuchsin, it all makes sense. If you
have the יוחסין yuchsin to be on a capital case, certainly you
have the יוחסין yuchsin for the lower standard of a monetary case.
But just because you can be on a monetary דיין dayan doesn't
mean you have the יוחסין yuchsin to be on a capital case.
So that all works beautifully if you're talking about יוחסין. yuchsin. But
if you're talking about this issue about theft and those types of
things,
אמאי
אינו ראוי?
amai eino
ra'ui? So he says, אמאי אינו ראוי? amai eino ra'ui? What would
be a case that somebody is not fit for doing capital cases?
דאיתזם בדיני נפשות. de'itazam bedinei nefashos. He was found to be lying,
he testified falsely in capital cases. So in that case ראוי לדון
דיני ממונות? ra'ui ladun dinei mamonos? How could you say they could
be כשר kosher for monetary cases?
And the... If that's true, you will never have somebody that's invalid
for capital cases that testified falsely about capital that will be kosher
for monetary cases. That makes absolute no sense. אלא פסול יוחסין קאי
הכא נמי פסול יוחסין קאי. Ela pasul yuchsin kai hacha nami pasul
yuchsin kai. So this whole case of the משנה mishna has to
be talking about the question of יחוס. yuchas. And then it all
makes sense. Somebody could have anyone who has the יחוס yuchas for
being on a capital case can have the יחוס yuchas will have
the יחוס yuchas for being on a monetary, but you could have
the יחוס yuchas for being on a monetary but not have proper
יחוס yuchas for being on a capital. Fine.
So this has nothing to do with our case, it doesn't prove
a סתם משנה stam mishna like Rabbi Meir. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא הכא Ela hacha finally now we're at the point we
were trying to make. אלא הכא קסתמלאן. Ela hacha kastamlan. Here's where
it is. דתנן Detnan we taught in a משנה. mishna. This sounds
like our משנה mishna but it's a משנה mishna Rosh Hashanah. אלו
הן הפסולין. Eilu hen hapsulin. The following people can't be witnesses: המשחק
בקוביא ומלווה בריבית ומפריחי יונים וסוחרי שביעית. Hamisachek bekubya umalve beribit umafrichei
yonim vesochrei sheviit. So far it's exactly our משנה. mishna. ועבדים Veavadim
and slaves. Okay, so it adds in a פסול דאורייתא psul deoraita
of slaves. But the real reason we're quoting this is for the
next line. זה הכלל Ze haklal this is the principle: כל עדות
שאין האשה כשרה לה אף הן אין כשרן לה. Kol edut sheein
haisha keshera lah af hen ein kesheran lah. Anything that a woman
is not כשרה keshera for because there's some testimonies a woman could
testify specifically about a husband, you know, about a man being lost
at sea, a husband drowning and so on, there are cases in
which they allowed they accepted the testimony of a woman. But anything
that's not those categories, anything that's not those exceptions,
so all of these people, you know, the gamblers etc. cannot be
witnesses for. Okay מני Mani who is that going like? אילימא רבי
יוסי Ilima Rabbi Yosi if it's Rabbi Yosi והאיכא עדות בדיני נפשות
Vahika edut bedinei nefashot that rule won't always be true. Because here
you have these people, these gamblers etc.
Really Rabbi Yosi's point is all of these people in our משנה
mishna that are invalid for monetary reasons, the gamblers, the person who
lent with interest, all of those things, Rabbi Yosi would say can
still testify in a capital case, right? That's Rabbi Yosi's position. So
he says, but this משנה mishna says if a woman can't testify
these guys can't testify. So it says according to Rabbi Yosi in
a capital case שאין האשה כשרה לה sheein haisha keshera lah a
woman can't testify והן כשרים לה vehen kesherim lah Rabbi Yosi would
say all of our cases in the משנה mishna can testify in
a capital case because just because they lie about money they won't
lie about life and death. So the fact that the משנה mishna
Rosh Hashanah clearly invalidates them for all testimony shows like Rabbi Meir.
That's actually a pretty good proof. אלא לאו רבי מאיר היא Ela
lav Rabbi Meir hi it must be that it's Rabbi Meir. So
you see that since it's saying everybody in our משנה mishna is
totally פסול, pasul, we say once you're פסול pasul for monetary cases
once you compromise yourself for monetary cases we're all still afraid you
will you're also invalid for capital cases. You're totally invalid as a
witness. So קם בר חמא נשקיה אכרעיה דרב פפא. Kam Bar Chama
nashkei achreia deRav Pappa. Bar Chama got up kissed Rav Pappa on
his feet that you know that he gave a פסק psak that
allowed him to throw out the witness say since you're a גזלן
gazlan you can't testify on a capital case. We go like Rabbi
Meir once somebody is פסול pasul they're פסול pasul across the board.
And that therefore maybe also you know was able to save this
person who was being accused and saved him from having to go
ahead and poke out his eye. וקבליה לכרגיה דכולי שני Vekiblei lechargia
dechulei shenei and he agreed to pay his taxes Rav Pappa's taxes
for all of his years you know because he was so grateful
that Rav Pappa allowed him to save this man. Now the interesting
thing here is again even though we rule like Rabbi Meir, so
bottom line is what this whole discussion was really telling us is
those people that are פסול pasul in our משנה mishna are they
also פסול pasul for capital cases? And the answer is yes. Even
though logically you could say just because they compromise here doesn't mean
they'll compromise for capital cases, Rabbi Meir takes a categorical approach. Nevertheless,
as the גמרא Gemara itself said, that's a jump to go from
there to Abaye that says that because you ate נבלה להכעיס neveila
lehachis you know which has nothing to do with testifying and nothing
to do you know with hurting someone that labels you as a
רשע rasha and that invalidates you as a witness. But nevertheless that
is how we rule like Abaye so we have two categories. If
you do an עבירה aveira that you're obligated that you're deserving of
lashes even if it's only you know בין אדם למקום bein adam
lamakom you're invalid and that's דאורייתא deoraita and if you do something
that shows that either testifies falsely against somebody in any area or
compromises and you do an עבירה aveira for monetary gain even though
you know without a rationalization then that would also invalidate you. That's
a רשע דחמס rasha dechamas and that has. And that has more
to do with the fact that, you know, we're afraid that you
will sell your testimony, but we do make it categorical to be,
you know, even פסול pasul for ממונות mamonos is פסול pasul for
נפשות, nefashos, and so on. Okay, so that is all like a
whole huge set of הלכות halachos around the category of what makes
somebody a פסול עד pasul eid because of עבירה. aveira. We're just
going to read very briefly this משנה mishna about who is a
פסול עד pasul eid for because of a relative and we will
unpack it tomorrow. ואלו הן הקרובים, Ve'elu hein hakrovim, the following are
considered to be the relatives who are פסול pasul as witnesses.
אחיו, Achiv, your brother. Now what you have to know is that
there's a general nomenclature to refer to degrees of relation in הלכה.
halacha. And it basically starts with the idea that brothers are considered
ראשון בראשון, rishon berishon, if you'd like imagine like you're going to
draw a family tree, anybody that's on that same level, brothers, give
them all number one, they're all level one. Okay, and the rule
is going to be and you'll see as we read through this
משנה mishna that anybody who's connected up to two-to-two. So if the
brothers are one and one, then the brothers, you know, ראובן ושמעון,
Reuven veShimon, then ראובן's Reuven son is number two, he's a down
a generation. So שמעון Shimon to ראובן's Reuven son is a ראשון
בשני. rishon besheini. All right. Now if שמעון Shimon has a son,
so that's another generation down. So if ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon are
ראשון בראשון, rishon berishon, then their sons, first cousins, are שני בשני.
sheini besheini. Okay, and that's basically the rule. Anybody is to that
degree of closeness, brother, uncle, cousins. Okay, brothers are ראשון בראשון, rishon
berishon, uncle is ראשון בשני, rishon besheini, cousins are שני בשני. sheini
besheini. They're invalid, plus if there's a similar relationship through marriage and
through wives, as we'll see, or sisters and husbands, that also would
be in that cluster. Okay, brothers, siblings, cousins, those are פסול. pasul.
We won't talk now and I should say father, son, and grandfather
and grandson, we'll talk about more complicated later. So let's take a
look at the משנה. mishna. ואלו הן הקרובים. Ve'elu hein hakrovim. אחיו,
Achiv, your brother. That's ראשון בראשון. rishon berishon. ואחי אביו, Ve'achi aviv,
your father's brother. Okay, so that would be, let's say ראובן's Reuven
son to שמעון. Shimon. All right, so that's שני בראשון. sheini berishon.
His father, the brother of his father. ואחי אמו, Ve'achi imo, your
mother's brother. Okay, so we also go by mother and it's the
same idea. That would be a שני בראשון. sheini berishon.
ובעל אחותו, Uva'al achoto, your sister's husband, because of the principle that
אשתו כגופו, ishto kegufo, so your sister's husband is like your brother.
Brother-in-law is like your brother, fine. So that's ראשון בראשון. rishon berishon.
ובעל אחות אביו, Uva'al achot aviv, your father's sister's husband, so that's
your uncle by marriage. But again because of בעל כאישתו, ba'al ke'ishto,
you know, אשתו כבעלה, ishto kiva'ala, בעל כאישתו, ba'al ke'ishto, so your
uncle by marriage is basically treated as your father's brother and we're
back to שני בראשון. sheini berishon. ובעל אחות אביו. Uva'al achot aviv.
ובעל אחות אמו, Uva'al achot imo, similar on your mother's side, okay,
your uncle on your mother's side. ובעל אמו, Uva'al imo, your mother's
husband, so your stepfather. But again because of אשתו כגופו, ishto kegufo,
that's like your father.
וחמיו, Vachamiv, your father-in-law. Same idea, right? Because you and your wife
are like one, so your father-in-law is like your father. וגיסו, Vegiso,
and your brother-in-law, okay. Same idea, your brother-in-law, guy married to your
sister, that's like your brother.
Actually,
I
said that wrong. Before we had your brother-in-law, the guy married to
your sister. This is your wife's sister's husband. Okay, so it's like
you're in-law twice. Okay, your wife's sister is your sister-in-law, and her
husband is also invalid. Okay, so that's sort of like
two אשתו כגופו. ishto kegufo. You and your wife are one, your
wife's sister and her husband are one, and that becomes like your
brother, but it's your brother-in-law in-law. All right. וגיסו. Vegiso. Now הן
ובניהן וחתניהן. Hein uveneihen vechataneihen. They are invalid, all the ones we've
mentioned, and their children, because all of these cases if you've been
paying attention are basically ראשון בראשון rishon berishon or ראשון בשני. rishon
besheini. So when you include their children, you get up to שני
בשני. sheini besheini. So if you're invalid with your uncle, you're also
invalid with your cousin. וחתניהן, Vechataneihen, and their sons-in-law. So your uncle's
daughter's husband is also with בעל כאישתו. ba'al ke'ishto. like your cousin
and therefore also invalid. וחורגו לבדו *ve-hurgo levado* and your stepson
alone. So when it comes to your stepson we don't say you
know all these other things that your stepson's son and your stepson's
what do you call it son-in-law etc. just your stepson but no
further. Why is that? Because everybody else here was basically a blood
relation once you say אשתו כגופו *ishto ke-gufo*, you know, my uncle,
my father's sister's husband is so once you combine אשתו כגופו *ishto
ke-gufo* that's my uncle effectively like a blood relation. Okay, but your
stepson is not a blood- a conceptual blood relation and therefore it
stops with him and it doesn't continue on. אמר רבי יוסי *Amar
Rabbi Yosi* זו משנת רבי עקיבא *Zu Mishnas Rabbi Akiva*, this is
all according to Rabbi Akiva that you go even by mothers okay
and even and you know and in all of these cases. אבל
משנה ראשונה *Aval Mishnah Rishonah* the first teaching was דודו *dodo* your
uncle ובן דודו *u-ven dodo* your cousin. So again it's uncle and
cousin so how is it different? וכל הראוי לירשו *ve-chol ha-raui leyorsho*.
It's only people it sounds like it's broader but it's narrower who
you could inherit.
So only basically people on your father's side and not on your
mother's side because inheritance if you remember from בבא בתרא *Bava Basra*
goes through the father's family. So without going through the whole list,
but it's just that somebody who let's take the case of your
mother's you know brother, you would never inherit from your mother's brother.
Okay, or no you could because he could die and there could
be no other relatives it goes to the mother and your mother
could die and it could go to you. But so you could
inherit from him but he could never inherit to you. Your property
would never go through your mother to your mother's brother. So you
would always look at can you inherit or not because if you
can inherit then the problem is that you're נוגע בדבר *nogea ba-davar*.
You might stand to gain if you can inherit. So that's a
very specific way of looking at it of not just about being
a relative it's about that you might gain from it and it's
therefore it's only because of somebody you could inherit. Okay? וכל הקרוב
לו באותה שעה *ve-chol ha-karov lo be-osah sha'ah* and anybody who was
close and by the way in that case about your mother's brother
it would the פסול pasul. *psul* would go one way and not
the other way very different from the teaching of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* that it's all just about relation. When you look at it
through the lens of inheritance your mother you could testify- you could
not testify for your mother's brother because you might inherit from him
but he could testify for you because he would never inherit from
you. Okay so that's the משנה ראשונה *Mishnah Rishonah*. Now וכל הקרוב
לו באותה שעה *ve-chol ha-karov lo be-osah sha'ah* anybody who was close
to you at the moment when the testimony took place okay either
or at the moment when he either when he witnessed it or
when he's coming to testify. היה קרוב ונתרחק *hayah karov ve-nisrahek* however
if somebody was a relative but now
he is no longer related okay there was a time when he
was related to you like you know it was your
father-in-law but then wife died or got divorced so he's no longer
your father-in-law okay
so that type of a case הרי זה כשר *harei zeh kasher*
just because you were invalid once you know as long as it
wasn't at the key moments of when the testimony was witnessed and
when you're coming to testify so now you go back to being
כשר *kasher*. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer* אפילו מתה בתו ויש
לו בנים הימנה *afilu mesah bito ve-yesh lo banim heimena* הרי זה
קרוב *harei zeh karov*. So going to this case of father-in-law which
is a case where they could be related and then the relation
stops because the wife dies, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says even after
the wife died if there were grandchildren then you know your father-in-law
and you you share you know they're your children and your father-in-law's
grandchildren you're still considered connected you're still invalid.
Okay last thing האוהב והשונא *ha-ohev
ve-ha-soneh* somebody who particularly is close and friendly with you or somebody
who really hates you those are also invalid. אוהב זה שושבינו *ohev
zeh shushbino* the אוהב *ohev* is the guy that served basically as
your groomsman at your wedding and רש"י *Rashi* says during the like
the time of your wedding of your week of your wedding they're
feeling very very close and they can't be objective. שונא *soneh* somebody
who hates you כל שלא דיבר עמו שלושה ימים באיבה *kol she-lo
diber imo sheloshah yamim be-eivah* somebody who has not spoken to you
three days running out of because you're having a fight. So if
you're in the middle of a fight and angry at somebody you
can't be objective in testifying against them. אמרו לו *amru lo* so
it's not exactly clear who said back to whom I mean before
we had that it was רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* was saying was
making a statement so is this entire thing until this point רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and all of this was משנה ראשונה *Mishnah Rishonah*
who is saying. Back to who? But anyway
he said back to him לא נחשדו ישראל על כך. No Jews
are not חשוד chashud that just because they're angry or they're friendly
with somebody that they'll testify falsely. You know if somebody has compromised
because of monetary reasons they're פסול. pasul If somebody is a relation
then they're maybe in a formal way פסול not because we're specifically
suspecting unless it had to do with the inheritance point. But just
because you're angry or you're close to somebody is not going to
be enough to get you know for we don't suspect Jews that
that will motivate them to actually testify falsely. Okay that was a
whole lot we will end here.